<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Lamenting vvord shewing how there is a desertion come upon us, and what are the evils, and with whom they are found that have procured it unto us / delivered by way of testimony unto the present work of God and against the defection of these times in the drawing back of many from it.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49118</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10758680</idno>
  <idno type="VID">45673</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248495477</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28763</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10758680</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45673)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1405:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Lamenting vvord shewing how there is a desertion come upon us, and what are the evils, and with whom they are found that have procured it unto us / delivered by way of testimony unto the present work of God and against the defection of these times in the drawing back of many from it.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Brewster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Presence of God.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45673:1"/>
            <p>A Lamenting VVord SHEWING, How there is a Desertion come upon us, and what are the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and with whom they are found that have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it unto us.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED, By way of Testimony unto the present Work of God, and against the defection of these Times in the drawing back of many from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Brewster</hi> at the <hi>three Bibles,</hi> at the West-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45673:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45673:2"/>
            <head>To all the Pretious Saints, who stand upon their Watch in this hour of Temptation.</head>
            <p>THat you are kept in watchfulness, in faith, and waiting for the Lord, whil'st others are eating and drinking with the drunken, and beating their fellow servants, is a mercy to your selves, a terror to the Enemy, and a refreshing to my soul.</p>
            <p>The Cause, Spirit and Interest of late so contended for by men, and owned by God, that has for some time lain dead and buried in the hearts of many, and in the defections of this day seems to be rising again among you, and to receive some revivings through your Faith, and a fresh supply of the Spirit of Grace upon you.</p>
            <p>As you have left behind you the low and carnal Principles of many, who propound no higher an issue to the late Administrations and Changes among us, than a worldly establishment of the Ecclesiastical and Civil State, and are looking after some better thing as provided for these last times, so the Lord direct you unto a right understanding what that good thing is that God will bring to pass in the Earth; that at least some of the tops of the Mountains and Rocks of that good Land may be in your eye, to strengthen and guid you whil'st you are labouring towards it, through the deeps of your infirmities, temptations and sufferings.</p>
            <p>And as both inward and outward afflictions have alwaies attended them that have took part with the Lord, so you may look to meet with the same in your selves, especially at this day, wherein this old corrupt World drawing near its end, and Satan knowing his time is but short, will both combine their most principle Agents, their most exquisite skill, force and power, if possible, to cut off the faith, and hope and rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of them that love and wait for the glorious Coming and Kingdom of our Lord Jesus; wherefore for your help in the way, let me put you in mind of a few things.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45673:3"/>
            <p>Let your eye be unto the Lord Jesus; as his Appearance and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is the consummation of our faith and hopes, and the great and last issue intended by Providence in the Changes and Revolutions that have been and may yet come to pass among us; so setting him in the eye of your faith, will be of best use to direct and help you in all those works and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs that lead ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unto: abide in Christ; so, whil'st the clouds and storms of temptations, troubles and sufferings, do beat upon your fl sh, in him you shall break through and overcome: you stand by faith; if you go forth in the confidence of your gifts, graces or any other privileges without the Lord, you shall fall as others before you have done and come to nothing.</p>
            <p>In the late Changes and shakings that have been among us, the Lord Jesus was that Spirit that moved the wheels, and disposed all as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning unto his last and great works of mercy and judgment, which he is determined to do, and wherein you should wait upon him in these last times: though the visible wheels seem to be at a stand, yet let your faith and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be going on, and you shall see, that our righteousness tarries not, and the judgment of our enemies slumbers not.</p>
            <p>Let not the treachery and declination of these times from the interest of the Lord Jesus trouble you, in the falling of many Stars, the slumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Virgins, the defection of the Civil and Military instruments, the roaring of the Sea and Waters, that is, the rage of the people; but let these things rather encourage you to look up, for the summer, your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draws nigh.</p>
            <p>As God has appointed a day, wherein Jesus Christ shall shine forth in all his dignities and offices, as Law-giver, Saviour, King and Judge, and wherein all Kingdoms shall serve and obey him, that is, all Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities and Constitutions both in the Church and Wold shall be disolved, or refined into a subjection unto him, his Law and Kingdom; so there shall be no settlement unto any Gov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnment or People, no success unto any Counsels or Policies new or old that shall rise up against the Lord or his People in this work: upon this stone have many of our Princes alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>len, and the wheels of them that are since come up in their place are troubled, drive heavily, and the waters, their troubles do encrease upon them: th refore stand fast in the Lord, my dearly beloved, looking for him; for yet a little while of darkness and trouble upon the World, of temptations and trials upon your selves, and He that shall come, will come, and will not tarry.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45673:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45673:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45673:4"/>
            <head>A lamenting Word.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I call to remembrance the times that are past, the days wherein the Lord walked in the midst of us, for a spirit of judgement to them that sat in Council, and for strength to them that set the Battail to the Gate; when through the faith and testimony of a praying people, and the presence of the Lord going before them, the Pillars of our earth began to shake, and the unrighteous to fall at his rebuke: And do consider the condition we are now brought back into, how our soul is bowed down to the dust, and our belly cleaveth to the earth; how the Lord hath cast off and put us to shame, and goes not forth with our Armies; makes us to turn back from the enemy, and hath scattered us among the Heathen; we are made a reproach to our neighbours, a scorn and derision to them that are round about us; wisedom is departed from our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellours, and the vision from our Prophets; I cannot but from these things, with some grief conclude that the Lord is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from us.</p>
            <p>Much time hath been spent in seeking unto many Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and more in impreachings and mutual recriminations, whilst the effect of all hath proved no better then a heighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our distemper, and our wound made more incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Surely it would be a work far more becoming a people in the condition we are in, to seek out what is that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and folly which hath been done among us, which hath provoked such a signal and continued discountenance from the Lord against us, and such a disaster and perplexity as is upon us: a short reflexion upon the times that are past, how
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45673:5"/> things were with us then, together with a due consideration of our present posture, how things are with us now, may be of much use by way of giving us light in this inquiry.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The light we had in the late War and changes, what it was.</head>
               <p>When the time came that God would judge and pluck down those two unbridled and bloody Powers, Monarchy and Prelacy, which had for many hundred of years divided the prey between the souls and bodies of the people of this Nation; that people among us whom he intended should serve him in this work, he was pleased to honour and furnish with three special gifts, with light unto the work, with faith in it, with a signal testimony of providence, giving victory in the work.</p>
               <p>The light that was given, was but little at the first, and came forth by degrees as we were able to receive it, and as there was need, God leading us by the hand, and as it were teaching us to go from strength to strength, from one difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to another in the beginning of the work, not knowing what would be the end of it; so that we were constrained at divers times to professe and publiquely declare, that our way was dark, and we knew not what to do untill the Lord was inquired, and further light vouchsafed.</p>
               <p>By that light we had we were directed, First, to a sight and discerning of the then present evil state of things, from which we groaned to be delivered: And Secondly, to a prospect of a better and more excellent way to be pressed after.</p>
               <p>As to the first, the whole frame &amp; constitution of things both in Church and State appeared to us to be leavened and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with Antichristian principles, destructive to the great interests of Civil and Gospel-freedome: Particularly, First, the exercise of an imposing power over the conscience in things of faith; together with the exercise of an Arbitrary power over the outward Rights and Liberties of men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>subjected and unaccountable to the Law or the people; the one of these being an intrenchment upon the prerogative of Christ, and the liberty of the spirit in his servants; the other upon the natural soveraignty and freedom of the people.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45673:5"/>
               <p>Secondly, We were led on to take notice of the conjunction and intermixture of Magistracy and Ministry, stretching themselves beyond their just capacities into each others line; the Magistrate constituting and imposing a Ministry and worship tempered to his interest; the Ministry strengthning it self in its dominion over the people by the Law of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate; and so by a mutual combination of their powers and interests serving each other, in order to the checking and resisting the work of Christ in every Age, which usually consisted in a greater growth of light and truth then their Interest or Temper could bear.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The Laws besides the supernumerariness of them, the obscurity and perplexity of words and notions, were observed to have many things in the body of them composed in times of Superstition and Tyranny, and hurtful and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive to the work of Reformation; and the practice of them to be corrupt, dilatory and chargable.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Persons were invested in Offices of Rule and trust, from corrupt and carnal respects, as Politique, Noble, Rich, &amp;c. whilst others furnished with a spirit of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were rejected; also men were chose into the Ministry according to Rules of humane qualification or national con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, whilst others of spirit and gifts more worthy of it, were removed into corners; by the one the streams of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and equity were stopped, by the other the streams of light and truth: the Heathenish state of things, worldly pomp, glory and preheminency were kept up by both, and the Gospel-way which is in simplicity, moderation and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly condescention, was excluded.</p>
               <p>Lastly, The way of Churching whole Nations and Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes, of Tithes, Patrons, presentations and innumerable things more were judged by us then to be no other then the remaines of Romish infection, as yet by reason of ignorance or Interest unpurged away.</p>
               <p>The removing far from us this corrupt frame of things, that way might be made for some better things then in our eye seems to me to have been the subject (as to the visible part of it) of that sharp contest lately in this Nation dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and gained through blood and prayer after a first, second, third and fourth War.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45673:6"/>
               <p>That better state of things which by the good hand of the Lord then upon us was discried, as that which might answer the ends of Providence, the expectations of the godly, and the exegencies of an unsetled Nation, was in the place of the Old, the erecting a new Basis, a constitution upon the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Gospel-principles, the whole building both in Church and State to be composed and framed according to Gospel-light and Rule; that is, so that all the several Offices and Powers committed to Christ, might be vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibly owned and exercised in the Nation, <hi>Isa.</hi> 33.22. <hi>For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord is our Judge, the Lord is our Lawgiver, the Lord is our King, he will save us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this way was that which Persons of clearest light and principles pressed after, and hoped to arrive at, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations from the Army was attested unto, so the wheels of many signal Providences, the interpretation of propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Scriptures sealed up before, and the Pulse of a faithful praying people seemed to aim and beat this way; it being to be supposed that the laying again the foundation of meer Civil Right and freedome, being no more then a worldly Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, would be a result no ways answerable to such spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial tokens and glorious deliverances from spiritual and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bondage as were bestowed upon us.</p>
               <p>And although such a foundation built up according to Gospel-pattern may not be conceived to be that very King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that shall be set up in the last days; yet would it be a dispensation expedient for such a people as we are, especially at such a time as this, who thereby might be put into a better capacity then as now we are of removing the stumbling stones, and preparing the Lords way, and so might put our selves into a posture of waiting and readinesse to receive him when he comes in his Kingdom.</p>
               <p>But if the backsliding part of this generation who have seen the goings of our God and King among us, shall say in their hearts, where is the promise of his coming? let all things continue as they were from the beginning, and shall draw back from that good work wherein they at first run well; yet let such as yet rule with God, and are faithful with the Saints, as wise men that know the time and their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45673:6"/> work, not suffer their eyes to sleep, nor their eye-lids to slumber, till the Lord will bring to perfection those glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things, whereof we have been in travail, but have not yet been able to bring forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The faith we had in the late Changes, what it was.</head>
               <p>Unto this light then vouchsafed the Lord added (as of special use for a people that are under such dispensations as we were) a faith to look for great things; the sum whereof in brief is as follows.</p>
               <p>That the set time was come, or at the doors, wherein the Lord would call to a reckoning the Rulers and Shepherds of the Earth, for the Male-administration of their Rule and Trust, in the exercise of Tyranny over men by the one, of Lordship over Gods heritage by the other; the effects where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of should begin in these Western Nations first, as being the undoubted horns of that Beast, to whom the cup of wrath is first to be given, before the rest of the Beasts; and this to be done first by the spirit of the Lord in his people, stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them up hereunto; after by the Lord himself, at his own appearing.</p>
               <p>That the Lord would pour out his spirit in such measures of light and zeal, and create in a remnant of his people such discerning and judgement, as should convince the world, winnow professors, discover and destroy the remaining Idols of Superstition, formality and worldly policy from among us; and hereby would take the advantage of blowing his Trumpet, and lifting up an Engine to other Countries, until he hath gathered a people out of all Nations; and then will set up the mountain of his house above all mountains; that is, will raise up his people to that height and greatnesse, that from thence he will manifest himself King over all the Earth, in giving the Law to all people, and rebuking strong Nations to the end of the Earth.</p>
               <p>That in order to the bringing of things to this glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult, the Lord will (as it is necessary) shake the Heavens and Earth, the Sea and dry Land; that is, will so trouble and shake the universal frame of things, both in the Civil and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45673:7"/> Ecclesiastical, in the Religious and Heathenish States, as shall occasion great commotions, perplexities and overturnings everywhere, and among all ranks and degrees of men; and no healing nor settlement shall be found, until he come whose the Kingdom is. The beginnings of which somewhat appeared in the days of <hi>Luther,</hi> but were more eminently revived by the late wonderful translations of Providence in these our Islands.</p>
               <p>Whatsoever lower aims many might have, whose princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples carried them no higher then unto some particular forms or models, into which they desired the ecclesiastical and civil constitutions might be cast; yet that the hopes and faith of many were raised up to look for these and such like great things, as hastening on in their several degrees and seasons, did undeniably appear by declarations from the Army, by the prayers and expectations, by the frequent assemblings, inquirings and consultations of a praying, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving people, to seek out what might be the intent and designation of Providence, and the work the Lord was about in our days; who hath promised a day wherein the Lord will be seen over them, and his decree shall go forth as the Lightning, and the Lord their God shall save them in that day, as the flock of his people, for they shall be as the stones of a Crown lifted up, as an ensign upon his Land, <hi>Zechariah</hi> 9.14, 16.</p>
               <p>Besides, the spirit that was upon many, stirring them up to pray, fight and go forth against all Parties and Interests in opposition hereunto, to bear up under the many deserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and discouragements by the falling away of false bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to follow God through interprizes and paths unpresi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented, highly offensive, and seemingly irregular, doth give further evidence what manner of faith was at work among us: the reason of which faith, and the means whereby it was begotten and increased in us, next unto the inward manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station of the counselling spirit of God, seemed to be the bringing to clearer light some Gospel-truths, the intepreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Prophesies, and the events of Providence answering thereunto, with other hints and tokens sought out by a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that had pleasure therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:45673:7"/>
               <head>The Testimony God gave to us in the late Changes, what it was.</head>
               <p>The Testimony that God gave unto us in a visible way, in the face of the world, and as a Crowning to the whole work, was Victory over the enemy, given in through a series of Providence, as much wondered at home, as famous and prodigious abroad.</p>
               <p>Whilst the foundation and subject of the War was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as of no more but a worldly nature, external rights and freedome, and the over-ruling part of Parliament and Army were such whose principles were but worldly and common, so long Providence shared the successe of Battail in a common and indifferent way between us and the enemy; but when by a remarkable turn of things God had laid aside, and took up other instruments, and new model'd Army of brighter and more refined principles, he forthwith let down the scale, consumed the enemy with a continual stroke, till he left none remain; concerning which, as an interview of some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular passages therein, these hints may be given.</p>
               <p>As their foundation was laid in wickednesse, so God poured confusion upon their Councels, made their way as the dark and slippery places, and cut off the spirit of their Princes in the day of Battail, whilst he shined upon the Councels and spirits of his people, and went forth before our Armies as in the Chariot of salvation; like as it was in the days of old, when God went forth before Israel in a cloud, which was darknesse to the Camp of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> whilst it gave light by night to the Camp of <hi>Israel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though they had the concurrence of worldly power and policy, usurpation, pomp and greatnesse, under the shadow whereof they trusted; yet all fell before the righteous and integrity of a believing, praying, everywhere despised people; as if the Lord would have us gather, that the time to take down all such interests with their Abettors was nigh at hand, that way may be made for the bringing in those better things which God hath reserved for these last days.</p>
               <p>When the commandments and inventions of men, Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary powers, constitutions and practises imposed in times of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45673:8"/> darknesse and tyranny were set up in a way of superiority over, and by force of Armes defended in opposition to the Government of Christ, liberty of Conscience, and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of common just and right; when things were thus, it pleased God to passe righteous judgement between the evill and the good, by rising up as a cruel and terrible one against all such Egyptian Task-masters, and yoakes of bondage; whence the wise in heart might know and consider, that henceforth no Authority that shall rise up, no weapon that is formed against the building up of Sion, against spiritual principles, and righteous interests shall prosper, but shall molder and be broken to pieces.</p>
               <p>After that this glorious cause and interest, and the friends thereof had got safe through, and triumphed over the power and policy of all secret and open enemies at home; it pleased God afterward to make it and his people a cup of trembling to all enemies from abroad that came against us: neither the reformed pretences of the Scottish Nation, nor the naval force and pride of the Dutch could save them from those signal and terrible rebukes, which their anger and hatred against us and our righteous cause, provoked the Lord to visit upon them. So then, what ayled you oh ye ancient Thrones of Monarchy and Prelacy, with your King and Armies, that ye fell down? thou <hi>Scotland,</hi> with thy three Armies at <hi>Preston, Dunbar, Worcester,</hi> that ye fled and were not? yet <hi>Dutch</hi> that ye sunk into the bottome of the Sea like a stone? was it not some bright beams from the face of the Lord Jesus, shining through the faith, the prayers, and the righteous cause of his people, that made them look fair as the Sun, clear as the Moon, and terrible as an Army with banners, that confounded your counsels, cut off your spirits, and consumed you to nothing?</p>
               <p>Thus it was with us in times past, when we leaned upon the Lord, when we followed him in untrodden paths, and ways that were not known; then the Lord was among us, making darknesse light before us, leading us on from one degree of light to another, from one mountain of salvation to another, having led us some dayes journeys into the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse, towards that Kingdom that he hath promised to set up in the last days.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45673:8"/>
               <head>The desertion that is now upon us, what it is.</head>
               <p>BUt after that God had subdued our enemies under us, cloathed us with salvations and victories, disposed the power into our hands, and thereby had put us into a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of performing the promises and paying the vows made to the Lord and his people in the day of our straights, we setled down into secu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity and ease, not attending what further duty might be incumbent upon us, to make further progresse in the good things begun until they grow up to their perfection; as if Providence had designed no higher ends in these acts of severity and goodnesse among us in throwing down one generation and setting up another, then the putting of his people into a condition of meer worldly freedome and quiet: So being raised up from a low and oppressed estate unto the seats of Authority and Rule, we fell in love with our new greatnesse; and being set up in a condition of outward security and freedome, we sat down at ease therein, and refused to follow the Lord through those further difficulties and trials whereby only can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained an entrance into the promised rest; and thus being turned from after the Lord, he is departed from us, and hath left us in the Wildernesse to be scattered in the darknesses, dreams and devices that we have chosen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The first symtome of the desertion that is upon us.</head>
               <p>THat the Lord is not among us as in former times, will appear too true, if our present condition, and the symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes that are upon us be but seriously observed.</p>
               <p>First, We are degenerated from those publique and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous principles, justice, faith, light, zeal and purity, whereby we were acted and moved to presse after worthy and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things, and are returned back to the dark and filthy principles of worldly policy, self-love, national conformity, and such like, building again the things that we sometimes destroyed:— let old administrations and formes of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, publique Instruments and proceedings be set up or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45673:9"/> laid aside, as they shall be found subservient or otherwise to the present works of providence, and the interest of <hi>Sion.</hi> Let all personall or particular interests inconsistent with the preservation and good of the whole body of the people be dethroned and abolished.—Let principles of light and truth, and a reformation of all things framed according thereunto be zealously pressed after, though the Nations be angry, the people moved, and all things thereby put out of course. All confidence in our selves or other men being laid aside, let us lean upon the Lord for light and counsel what to doe, and follow after him as he shall go before us in his word and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Such things as these enlivened with a spirituall savour and heat from the Lord, were upon the hearts of many for a season, who are since fallen in love with that woman <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> which has seduced them to commit fornications with her; to wit, the present Antichristian and corrupt frame of things both in Church and State, known by its pomp, luxury, greatness, and the pleasures of this world, which has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready shaken, but is not yet removed from among us.</p>
               <p>No lesse noble and worthy were those works unto which a door was opened to us of the Lord, and were at first pressed after by us, whilst our integrity remained with us, to wit, the doing execution upon all such Authorities, Laws, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions as had been erected and continued for the defence of Tyranny, Usurpation, single Prerogative, lording Clergy, &amp;c. and as had by force and persecution put a check upon the common Right and Freedom of men, and upon the Light and Liberty of Christians. The purging out from the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, Ordinances, and Churches, &amp;c. all mixture of humane Contrivance, State policy, and Romish devices, to the intent that all proceedings therein might be reduced under the sole Authority of Gospel-rule, and the Unction of the Spirit. The framing of all things both in Church and State accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to such just rules, and the disposing all power into such faithfull hands, as that the Administrations on Earth might submit themselves to be ordered according to that fuller measure of Righteousnesse, light, and truth, as these last daies look for, untill the Kingdoms of this world become the kingdoms of our Lord and his Christ.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:45673:9"/>
               <p>But now that spirit and heart we had to these things is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from us, and nothing is more minded by most then the securement and preservation of those very corrupt interests which by many providences, faith and prayer were designed for destruction: remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do thy first works, or else I will come against thee quickly, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A second Signe.</head>
               <p>ANother sign that the Lord is not among us as in former yeers appeares herein, that our singlenesse of heart to the Lord is gone, &amp; we are joyned to other Lovers: it pleased God of late to visit these our Northern Islands with some brighter beams then he vouchsafed to other Nations, and to chuse these ends of the earth where he would begin to set up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Sonne above all the oppressive and Antichristian powers of the world; then he alone was our King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellour, our Captain in the field, then we waited for his light alone to shew us our way, and to lead us through all our streights and feares; when his grace shining forth through the preaching of the Gospel had freed us from a spirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage within, and by a wonderfull succession of providences had delivered us from many yokes of bondage without, then it was upon our hearts that the admittance of Jesus Christ unto the exercise of his Regall Power and Soveraignty over us, would be the only expedient to make up all our breaches, to heale all our distempers, answer all our exigences, and make us a name, a joy and a praise in all the earth; then we saw it was not a King, nor Nobles, nor any imposed Liturgy, nor a Reformed Directory, nor the Congregated waies, nor any thing whatsoever that could deliver us, but to have the Lord himselfe in the midst of us, and to be all taught of him, that is, to have his Word and Spirit no longer as an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but to be set up above all, so as to direct, judge, and bear rule in all Cuuncils, interests and affairs amongst us.</p>
               <p>But now that a little space of breathing from the former troubles hath been given, we have no more need of him, we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45673:10"/> have chosen us other Saviours; we are Lords, we reigne, and are full, and come no more at him; without him we have Judgement and Councel to steer our course aright, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage all proceedings with success: formerly, before our dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult or new undertakings there were seen among us, tears and prayers, and travellings of soule; the Churches and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faithfull Saints were sent to for counsell, prayer, and help, but now we can without God constitute Governments, establish a State-Ministry, make warre, and conclude peace; we can rear up again the shaken walls of Monarchy and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church-way, defame, imprison, and persecute all that will not bow to it; we can doe all this and the Lord not know of it, see how this filthinesse is spread over the whole body of profession; The Presbytery sometimes honourable for their faith, zeale, and purity; in shaking off the yoke of Prelacy, how did they after assume that preheminence to themselves which they suffered under before; and deny that Christian liberty to their brethren which themselves at first groaned after. Independency and the Baptized way, preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and lovely at the first for their spirituall simplicity and singleness to the Lord, not leaning upon the Authorities of the world either for promotion to themselves or prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence to their way, how are they since clasped about the Powers and Pillars of the world; many chiefe leaders be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chaplains, Triars, Masters, and in all Dignities and Offices for worldly advantage; and so are become the chief stones and beams in this old worldly frame of things, by their gifts and parts renewing the lustre thereof, which themselves had before in contempt and detestation. The Army no lesse terrible abroad for their zeal against Kingly interest, then beloved at home for their principles of Light, Liberty, and tenderness; displaying the Banner, and sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an alarm to a spiritual Kingdom, having the Lord going before them, and they following him through fire and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and many dangerous passages; how are they now become mercenary, holding the Sword in defence of an Interest for the ruine whereof it was first drawn. The professing part of the people, how are they set down at ease, some in forms,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45673:10"/> others in notions, divided about gifts, priviledges, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions, while <hi>they lie upon beds of Ivory, and stretch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves upon their Couches, and eat the Lambs out of the flock, and the Calves out of the stall, that chant to the sound of the viall, and invent to themselves instruments of Musick like David, that drink wine in howls, and annoint themselves with the chief Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but they are not grieved for the afflictions of Joseph,</hi> Amos 6.4.</p>
               <p>We have been looking for salvation to mountains and hils, to Authorities, Army, the persons and actings of men, whilst that wherein our salvation is, to wit, the further rising and going forth of that blessed Sunne whose beams have already dawned upon us, and a professed subjecting of our selves and affairs thereunto, has not been regarded; but the confusion and emptiness that God already has, and may further write upon all these props may fulfill that word upon us: <hi>Ye shall be ashamed of the Oakes which ye have desired, and ye shall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded for the Gardens that ye have chosen,</hi> Esay 1.29.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A third Signe.</head>
               <p>A Discerning the signs of the times, and what is our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent work (a favour sometimes vouchsafed of the Lord) is now taken from us, which is a further sign that the Lord is departed.</p>
               <p>The presence of God with his people representing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self under such names and resemblances as suited with their present dispensation, was that Star that led his people in all former Ages, and of late in our days, unto a disce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning both of time and judgement, and of what Israel ought to do; as it is written, <hi>In thy light we shall see light;</hi> that is, the appearance of Christ to his people, is that which gives them light to know both the present work of God and their duty therein; so it was to the seaven Churches in <hi>Asia:</hi> If God communicates his counsels to any concerning things not seen as yet, either the judgements or mercies that he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to reveal in the world, it is a sign of his presence and favour with such; <hi>Shall I hide from Abraham that thing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45673:11"/> which I do? Gen.</hi> 18.17. The Wife of <hi>Manoah</hi> said unto him, If the Lord were pleased to kill us, he would not at such a time have told us such things as these, <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.23. As on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, it is a sign of a man or a people from whom God is for the present departed, to be left to the darkness of humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivements, without any voice or vision of God concerning the present administration, and their duty therein.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Jerusalem</hi> knew not the day of their visitation, their house was left unto them desolate, and thenceforth they saw him no more unto this day: When the late Rulers and Prelacy of <hi>England</hi> would not see nor consider the work of the Lord that was to appear in our Land, the Sun set over their heads, and their place was left empty: The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations since, that have lost that judgement and heart to the work they sometimes had (as it is to be feared) are left and laid aside as of no more use, at lest in those more excellent and glorious works which remain behind.</p>
               <p>Whilst the Kingdom and work of our Lord Jesus was beautiful in our eyes, and our zeal and labour, and patience, and sufferings therein abounded, then we had a sight into those great things God was about, <hi>(viz.)</hi> desolations upon all Tyranny and usurpations, upon all the corrupted Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions and Governments of the world, by the brightnesse of Christ<hi>'s</hi> rising among his people: But now security, fulnesse and conjunction with Antichristian interests hath blinded us so, that we cannot see a far off, to the end of them; a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest witnesse of the truth whereof is with sadnesse of heart to be seen everywhere at this day; the common Assemblies generally being unsensible of it; the gathered Churches for the most part silent; the Court carelesse in it; the Army having deserted it as to any further appearing for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to perfection that blessed interest, which providence, faith and prayer has been in travell with.</p>
               <p>Whosoever shall observe the posture we are found in at this day, how divided among our selves about the time and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensation we are under; some saying, lo here is Christ, that is only within, denying his Person or visible Kingdom; others, lo there, in their order and way, limiting the presence and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45673:11"/> work of Christ within their party or perswasion; others say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the time is not come that the Lords house should be built, because they would first build their own cieled ones: others dwellers among the Moles and the Bats, saying, no such time either is or will be at all; all things continue as they were from the Creation, God will doe no new thing in the Earth; these things conclude that the tract and print of the footsteps of the Lord in his work among us is hid from our eyes.</p>
               <p>When our former troubles had beset us round, and our fears within were as many as our fightings without, and the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death was written upon all waies and means of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scaping by any visible hand, then we cried unto God out of the wilderness and low place; and the Lord rent the Clouds and came down in his still voyce into our hearts, in tempests and whirlwinds upon our enemies; then the Lord Jesus shone upon us, and his savours upon our hearts melted us into trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and sorrow over the corruptions of our Rulers, teachers, and people, Laws and Government, over the darknesse, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inward slavery upon our own and all Nations; then we saw that the taking down of this old, worn, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated fabrick of things both here and all the world over, to make way for glory and beauty to dwell in all lands, was that which providence aymed at in his dispensations among us; when we shall be weary of our new-dressed Idols both in Religion and state, and shall finde them unable to defend us from those desertions from God, and afflictions from men that our backslidings have already in part and may further bring upon us; then it may be we shall cry to him that redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med us from our first bondage, and then in the mount will the Lord be seen, and his work appeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A fourth Signe.</head>
               <p>DEadnesse to God, and servitude to men is entred in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us in the place of that free, fervent, and active spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that was sometimes upon us; a sad token that the Lord is not among us. While the Lord Jesus was in the midst of us, as the great invisible wheele, then all the other wheeles moved
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45673:12"/> in their courses swiftly; all instruments whether in Councill, Army, or Christian assemblies, moved in their severall stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with vigour and judgement; all ministred something, such as they had, towards the work; some brought carved work, some fine linnen, others badgers skins, every one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they had received▪ as the dew lay upon <hi>Gideons</hi> fleece, when all the earth w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s dry, so while all other people and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were dead and dry as to the work, the spirit of the Lord was with his people, whereby they were stirred up and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, some to engage against the Outworks of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Courts, Armies, imposed innovasions and superstitions; some to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saile the very pillars thereof, Monarchy and Prelacy; some by their pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cious doctrines of Grace righteousness, and peace by Christ alone vanquished her mists and fogs of Legality and worldly elements, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eby the soules of men were held in darkness and bondage; others revealed her secret and more covered parts, so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght to lay flat all her Bulwarks and Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, Forts and Towers throughout the land. Such bright and pleasant beams from the Lord Jesus, after a long and dark winter night, shined through the Gospel and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations of providence as set on fire the desires of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny after him, and their zeale against whatsoever hindred the advancement of him in the exercise of his power as King of Saints here, and afterward as King over all Nations: and such holy extasies of love and zeale to Christ and Zions cause were upon a people among us, as rendred them unto a prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssing people in both Nations that had not like light and zeale, suspected and publickly censured to be a fanatick, delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and Enthusiasticall Army and people; and also such high and heroick resolutions carried them on, as made them a wonder, and a dread to all the Nations about us.</p>
               <p>Oh, but what is now become of this blessed people? doe they not lie as the bones in the valley dead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd dry? the eyes of many being sometimes annointed with the eye-salve of Gospel and spirit teaching became so bright and clear, as to take a prospect of that house or universal state of things promised to be set up, how are they now grown dim, and cannot see beyond the present corrupt state of things? the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45673:12"/> ears that were sometimes open to the voice and counsels of the spirit, to rule and teach, and steer thereby, how are they now stopped, and we sail by another compasse? we are like men that began to build, and the first stones towards a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly building were laid in our days, but finding that the raising of it up to an higher pitch would put us to more pain and difficulty then we are willing to suffer, we are become dead as to any further proceeding therein; is not this written upon the face of all things?</p>
               <p>Consider our teachers, our Gospel-teachers (I mean) such who have been unto the Church of Christ as the Angels of the Lord, now become silent and dead as to pressing forward to the things before, the Renovation and restorement of all things by the further comings forth of Christ.</p>
               <p>—Our Governours and chief Captains, who sometimes were as a hearth of fire among the wood, and as a torch of fire in a sheaf, devouring the wicked on the right hand and on the left, are now dead as to bringing up their good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to any further growth and maturity; the main Pillars of the old, corrupt, enslaving and Antichristian interest yet standing, and the former dispensations and works of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and an answerable subjecting of all things thereunto being not regarded; — the fervent desires and longings that were among many Saints after a fuller reformation, and their sorrows and fears for the present corruption are for the most part ceased; — the blessed Gospel-d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctrines are grown dusky, the teachers are waxen dim, the work is at a stand, and the foundations thereof are covered in the rubbish of the old, corrupt interests brought in again; and there are few that lay it to heart, or have any judgement or might to discern or give warning of this evil time; se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, division, worldly advancement and seducing spirits, having eaten out that first simplicity, light and love that was amongst us.</p>
               <p>Add unto all this our servitude unto men; they among us that once disputed the interest of Christ, liberty of Saints, and the common good of the Nation, against the highest and proudest enemies thereof, how are they now become
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45673:13"/> the servants of men, acquiescing in, and for advantage sake preferring the constitutions, commandements and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique devices of men, men corrupted from the first purity and practice, before the promoting of the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cious cause of Christ, and the conscience of their duty and service the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ein; of whom one may take up that ancient parable, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.14. <hi>Issachar is a strong Asse, Couching down between two burdens, and he saw that rest was good, and the Land that it was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, and bowed his shoulder to bear, and became a servant unto tribute.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A fifth sign that the Lord is departed.</head>
               <p>THe heavens have been for some season silent, and little or no answer of God among us, a further s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n that the Lord is not among us as in former years; — the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ible ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrations of Gods providence being Gods voice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he sometimes spake graciously to us, and terribly to our enemies, have been for too long a time withheld, and the windows of heaven shut, and we have been left under many darknesses and desertions; while the interest of Christ and his people was in our hands, and the debate about it was depending between us and our enemies, then the Lord went before us through the flouds of many waters, all the several parties that rose up against us; neither the enchantments of <hi>Balaam,</hi> nor the Armies of his King, from one hill or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the could prevail against us; such witnesse God gave unto us by a continued series of providence so visibly and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously for us, as made that noble cause among us and the Adherents unto it a terrour and astonishment to all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about us; but when this cause began to be declined, and other fruit to appear, the countenance of heaven also chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged toward us, since which time our wheels have driven heavily, our Armies are scattered by the Heathen, proceedings at home are fruitlesse, and expeditions abroad do as little; we looked for much, and loe it came to little; and when we brought it home, God did blow upon it; why, saith the Lord of Hosts, because of mine house that is waste, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45673:13"/> ye run every man unto h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s own house; therefore the heavens over us are stayed from dew, and the earth is stayed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om her fruit <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.9, 10.</p>
               <p>In days past the spirit of the Lord was among us, making a way for us in the Wildernesse, in paths untrodden before, and a way in the deep waters, in ways which no man had passed through before; he put the honour upon us to bind our Kings in chains, and our Nobles in fetters of Iron; then all inst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uments moved swiftly, and work went on apace; one work after another was set before us, and successes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered and came in one upon another; those yoaks that our Fathers groan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and bled under for many years, we shook off in a few months; those bulwarks of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Monarchy and Prelacy that had been taking root for many hundreds of years, were thrown down in one day; such clearnesse of jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ement and willingnesse of heart was among us, as made hard work easie, and rough services smoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h; the Lord ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his pleasant gales and warming beames for our succour in the work; all our works were crowned with gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry and successe, whilst sincere affections to Christ were our principle, and the advancement of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im in his recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling grace and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eigning glory was our end in all.</p>
               <p>But into what a confusion and desertion we are now fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, they have little spiritual eye-sight that cannot discern; Private and lesser interests are attended, whilst that which is of the highest and general concernment is at a stand; unto the further prosecution whereof there is no skill nor strength, nor life, nor heart; — while reformation moved upon the faith and prayers, tears and travels of Gods people, it was as an Engine upon the wheels, or as a Ship with wind and tyde; but since these were deserted, how do our Pilots towe and hale, and weary themselves in vain? what successe have most Teachers h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d upon their people, but to Preach them into lukewarmn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ss and slumber, sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they left to be a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, waiting people, or the communion of them that are such? How has a victorious Army been scattered, since they left off to be a praying Army? how many interruptions and rebukes have the Rulers met with since they sailed in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45673:14"/> bottom, and by another wind and tyde? whole yeers cannot bring forth now what monthes, weekes, and daies produced formerly; and that work that was carried to some boservable height in a troublesome time, is found too hard to be proceeded in in a time of peace; oh that we would consider the hand that is upon us, and how faith, prayer, and the smiles of providence, and together therewith the work of the Lord are departed from us to another people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The sixth Signe.</head>
               <p>IT appears by what has been said, that our soule is brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and the outward state of things too, yet we have no mind to be healed, nor to heale one another, and offers of healing in the way it may be had are not accepted, which may be added as one sign more that the Lord is gone: they that had pitty and shewed compassion upon us in our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer troubles, when our burdens were heavier then our groanings, and by their spirituall gifts and righteous Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrations as fathers and nurses did nourish and feed us in the beginning of the day, how are their bowels now shut up that they have no compassion towards the travel of their soule whom they have begotten in Christ Jesus!</p>
               <p>When the former shepherds, Kings and Prelates had for a long time exercised Lordship and cruelty over us, and after them others of a more Reformed stamp rose up and sought the preeminence, then God raised up shepheards who for a season fed us with the better pasture of judgement and justice, Light and truth; then there was bread and balme in the hand to refresh the many hungry soules and bruised shoulders which the yokes and bonds of the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressors had made upon us; but now that we are as sheep scattered by seducing spirits, or worldly interests, whereby many are become sick, weak, and many fallen asleep, and we in a condition (if grace prevent not) of relapsing into our first darkness and slavery, yet how few are there that have an eye of pity, or a word of healing for us? we are like
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45673:14"/> a man wounded, that being vexed with pain is full of fury and anguish, and troublesome to every body: so we being wounded with the rebuke of the Lord, are of a crooked and bitter spirit, hurting and offending one another, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving neither healing in our selves, nor accepting it from others.</p>
               <p>I know we have sought to many Physicians that we might be healed; but our cold, formall, and generall tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings, and shreds and broken pieces of Reformation in Governtment, are but as they that sewed pillows, and dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with untempered mortar, which profited not. There are breaches and sores in the body, the visible state of things, but the distemper lies in our vitals; our faith is gone, our first love is lost, the Cause of Christ lies buried among us, and our hearts are dead unto it.</p>
               <p>And whereas there is but one way remaining, which our former faith and experience, and a praying People at this day do tell us of, and propound unto us as the only healing dispensation both unto Church and State; to wit, a subjecting of our souls and lives, our Ministry and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, our Laws and Constitutions, with all Interests and Affairs, unto that Kingdom and Authority, and those De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs and Works foregoing it, which the Prophecies of old, and Providences of late have intended for these last times, yet this way and course is of no acceptation with us; but however pretended to formerly, and in the judgement of spirituall Gospel-Christian, of more weight then any other that has been proposed, is now excluded as a seditious Principle, destructive to the present state of things, and the work of a fanatick, brain-sick, and unsound Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; whence our Conclusion appears too true, That the Lord is not among us as formerly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:45673:15"/>
               <head>The sins that have brought this desertion upon us, what they are, and with whom they are found.</head>
               <p>NOw to make an enquiry what those sins committed among us may be, which have provoked the Lord to bring upon this Generation, formerly a People of right noble Principles and glorious Atchievements, such a deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted estate as it now lies under, seems to be a work becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all such Christians as would turn away the present re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes that are upon us; in which undertaking although the evil may appear more grosly and vis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bly upon some par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular parties, more then upon others: yet forasmuch as upon just and impartiall search I finde no parties nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons whatsoever, neither my self nor others, that can stand aside and say, we are free from partaking in those sins that have provoked this cloud upon us; therefore in plainness of heart, without fear or flattery, I shall briefly declare what things I have against every one, from the greatest to the least among us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The sin of the Army, what.</head>
               <p>TO begin with the Army first; these, whlle a Gospel-spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it was upon them, enflaming them with zeal to the Lord Jesus, with love to all Saints, and with a spirit of judgement to see righteousness and freedom brought forth unto all men, the Lord forgave the many haltings, slips, and infirmities that through darkness or temptation th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y were overtaken with; but since then an evil heart of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is found in them, in not following the Lord unto the perfecting of that work, the foundation whereof was laid by their own hands, that frame of spirit that was upon them when they were led forth against the oppressive and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian interests, would have carried them on (if worldly advancement and security had not quenched it) unto a more excellent way to a more perfect and spirituall Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation then yet is brought forth.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:45673:15"/>
               <p>While their work was against the outer-courts and outer-works of <hi>Babylon,</hi> onely the bricks and clay, and grosser things thereof, they had spirit and faith for service; but when they came into her ceiled Chambers and Marble To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, her golden wedge and goodly garment, these they spared from the sword: while Monarchy and Prelaticall Clergie, and the former state of things appeared in a more loathsome and ugly form, so long the Sword had no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on them, till they were cut off; but no sooner did these appear again under new names; and a more comely habit, but they were admitted again unto their first power, seat, and authority as before, and accepted into favour and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces as much as ever.</p>
               <p>When the Army was labouring in streights, difficulties, and perillous undertakings, and the Lord alone appeared unto them as their light &amp; comfort, then their hearts were tender, and their eyes enlightened to behold the King in his beauty, and the things that were afar off; then they saw many things amiss among us, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in the Government, will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to have been long exercised instead of judgement and justice; humane policy and contrivance to be still set up above the dictates of sanctified Reason and Gospel-light. In the Magistrates, a declination from their first Principles of light and zeal, and from the just expectations of their godly and faithfull adhering friends. In the Law and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioners of it, they saw many Statutes, Customes, and Proceedings kept up, that were imposed in times of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Superstition, and exercised to the hinderance of light and Reformation, and to the prejudice of Christian and Civill Liberty. In the Ministry, much Antichristian leven, as the investure into it worldly, the maintenance of it worldly, and the fruits of many in it, no better then Philosophy and vain deceit, teaching for Doctrines the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinations of their owne brain, or the commandements of other men: In the whole frame of things, such corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, rottenness, and decay, as that they judged a reduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all things unto pure Gospel-rule, and just and spirituall Principles (a thing never done before) would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45673:16"/> prove the onely thing that would answer the designation of so many glorious Providences, the faith of Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the present exigency of things as they stood with us; which would consist in giving the preheminence unto the Peoples safety, above personall prerogative; unto the Word of God and Law of Christ, above carnall Reason and the politick contrivances of fleshly wisdome; unto spirituall gifts above humane qualification; and in owning and exalting the Kingdome of Christ on Earth above all righteous Principles of State-policy, or Nationall-interest whatsoever. And such a state of things they judged by faith and well-doing as well attainable as promised; <hi>for brass I will bring gold, and for iron I will bring silver, and for wood brass, and for stones iron; I will also make thy Officers peace, and thine exactors righteousness,</hi> Isa. 60.17.</p>
               <p>But when after finall Victory over the common Enemy, having tasted and surfeted with the sweetness of ease and rest, they found the further progress in the Worke would expose them to a further juncture of difficulties yet behind; instead of applying themselves to the Lord for new oyle and trimmed Lamps, a further supply of light and faith (as they had alwaies done in like case before) they betook themselves under pretence of avoiding Anarchy and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, into a new contrived way of their own, built upon the old Arbitrary and carnall Principles; and sheltering themselves under the shadow thereof, did thereupon put a stop unto all further proceedings in the Work; and so by degrees are relapsed into those dark and defiled Principles, as they were ashamed of before.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:45673:16"/>
               <p>The beginning of this desertion I observed with some grief of heart, did too visibly appear in the Officers imedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon their return from that crowning victory at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester;</hi> their frequent meetings unto prayer and consultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were then intermitted, and after some Months were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived for a little space, and produced some faint and langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing addresses to the Authority then in Being; their spirits grew dull and heavy, the sense whereof moved one of them in a speech of an hour long, with many tears to bewail his own and others slips, and another of them with much fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency, to urge the prosecution of the cause of his dear Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus; this being the time of the expiring of their zeal as a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing coal of fire.</p>
               <p>Unto this unbelief they have added further offence against God, in sitting down at ease <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the pleasures of this unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed state of things, whil'st the afflictions of <hi>Joseph,</hi> the despised cause and people of God are not remembred; the victories and salvations vouchsafed them of God, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and honors they have received from men, have put upon them such a glory and greatness, that they are fallen in love with their present condition; so that the preservati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of themselves in these fleshly privileges has so taken up their hearts, as that they are dead unto any further promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of that blessed work, which the Lord has yet to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his people, and by them upon the Rulers, States and Kingdoms, and interests of all Nations; the present state of things pleasing them so well, as that they have a jealous eye against whatsoever would loosen the roots of it, and in defence therof have made shipwrack of their first principles, and have taken up such mercenary, treacherous, and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian principles, as (whereas they were a beauty and sweet savor before) have rendred them a stink and contempt unto the people; it being to be feared that they succeding that wicked Generation that is fallen, in their houses and posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, they have partaked too much in their sins, and do now inherit their dark, corrupt, and Anti-christian principles which were their ruin: whether by these sins they have not provoked the Lord to leave them unto this their dark, dry, and unfruitful state, Oh that they might consider.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:45673:17"/>
               <head>The Sin of the Powers that have been, and are.</head>
               <p>AS concerning the Powers, this Nation has had variety; an hasty succession of one Power after another, the Government having been transmitted from one unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, until it has passed through the hands of all or most par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties among us, from the grossest to the purest: some of these there were, that for a season suited their Administrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the present designs of Providence, and exercised their power in a zealous and well guided subserviency unto that grouth of light and reformation God determined to bring forth; while they did so, the Lord breathed upon their Counsels, and lifted up their horn above the horns of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy and Prelacy, that had tyrannized before, and the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Judah,</hi> the People of God were their strength in the Lord of Hoasts their God: Instead of all other Rules of State-policy in use before, they were by a good hand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected unto a better Rule, to wit, that the time of favouring <hi>Zion</hi> and of doing great things was come, and that all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrations of Government ought to intend and look to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that, or should be broken; while they steered by this point, they were led through many dangerous shelves and boisterous seas, unto many pleasant shores and refreshing harbors of victories and salvations; but when they had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come most of their fears, and had brought things unto that state as answered their principles, and satisfied their interests, they setled into security and ease, and so lost the sense of that duty incumbent upon them, either as to any fuller redress of common grievance, or to any fuller reformation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might have been capable to have served the Lord in his dispensations towards <hi>Zion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The neglect hereof became also the sin of the succeeding Powers unto this day that came up after, whereby the Lord has been, and yet is provoked to deny success to their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Assemblies and proceedings, and to deny unto the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the benefit of receiving by their hands any healing or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45673:17"/> cure at all: the introducing and establishment of another Interest, to wit, the present state of things, being that which has buried their first Light, and Zeal, Vows and Engagements out of sight and mind; and in the place thereof has bgotten in them a lamentable darkness unto the further improvement of those first blessed principles, in the prosecution of that first glorious Cause, in order unto those approaching good things that have already dawned upon us.</p>
               <p>And until all private, personal, and self-advancing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest be laid aside by those in power, and that first prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple be assumed again, to wit, The submitting all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs and interests, all exercises of Rule and Power unto the help a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d furtherance of that shaking renovating work and Kingdom of the Lord Jesus, and the admitting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences, Prophesies, and former dispensations for a gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Rule, before all reason of State whatsoever; until it be thus, I do not expect that any parties of men, or forms of Government, whether by One or Many shal ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minister that health and cure to this Nation, as the nature of our sickness and wound calls for: God will not bless the most righteous principles, nor most reformed preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, when they are impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved either against, or not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that which is his special work in any age: <hi>Be wise th refore oh yee Kings, be instructed yee Judges of the earth; Kiss the Son lest he be angry:</hi> Yee are busied about lesser Matters, while yee neglect the weightier, Judgment, Mercy, Faith, and the love of God, the taking off yokes, and breaking bonds, the purging out of the old scum, and the new defilements that are found in Government, Ministry, Court, and upon the whole frame of things: a spirit unto this is witheld from you, because there is sin found among you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:45673:18"/>
               <head>The Sin of our Teachers.</head>
               <p>THere is also found folly and sin among our Teachers, which has added affliction to the misery; I speak of such, who as the brighter Stars in our heavens, have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened unto us the knowledge of Gospel-misteries in a clearer way, and in fuller measures of light and comfort unto dark and wounded sinners, than others had done before; by means whereof the knowledge of the Lord Jesus did so cover our Land, as that the mists and fogs of former darkness, the yoke and spirit of bondage, which bowed down both ours and our fathers necks, Legality, Superstition and Tyranny, began to give place and vanish away: they were for a season as burning and shining Lights; their Doctrine kindled such a fire in the hearts of many, as burnt down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he old, corrupted, National Church-state, with the Pillars and Gates thereof, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and Prelacy, Court, and Conclave; their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine sent forth such a Light as gave a just and worthy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement unto Grace above all Creature-works; unto Christ as sole Law-giver in the Churches, above all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional or Politick Jurisdict on; and unto the Unction and gifts of the Spirit above all School-learning, or humane qualification whatsoever; insomuch as old things began to pass away, and a glimpse of better things appeared, a new Church, new Government, new King, and new World to be looked for.</p>
               <p>But these Teachers being had in high esteem for their works sake, and having received double honor, instead of giving the glory to their Master, took it to themselves; and looking upon themselves as excelling many in Gifts, as embraced of many Christians, as honored of great Men, they fell in love with these their fleshly privileges; and thereby were led aside to seek after honor to their Gifts, ease to their Persons, and establishment to their Interests, and so neglected the promoting of those preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45673:18"/> and glorious Truths, which themselves had travel'd with before, and which rendred them as a sweet savour unto God, and as the Angels of the Lord to many of his People; and so by degrees at last fell into a compliance with that very Interest under a new name and disguise, which themselves had abandoned before, as under the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable names of Tyranny and Anti christianism: some of them leaving the work of the Church for a lazy Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge life; and the Ministry of the Word to attend upon Philosophy; leaving the Communion of Christians for the treasures and promotions of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> house, chusing rather these treasures of <hi>Egypt</hi> than the reproach of Christ; — O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers become Tryers, Lords over their breth en, exercising that Authori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y by humane deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which themselves had contended against before, as robbery to the Churches of Christ: — and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with their whole Churches fallen into such a slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, security and ease in present things, as that they have lost the exercise of their spiritual senses to discern the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised good things to come, and what is their present duty in order thereunto: wherefore the Lord has brought upon many of our Teachers a sore desertion for their sin, which may be seen herein.</p>
               <p>First, in the loss of that faith, light, and zeal they had in the beginning of the day, and which the further work of the day cals for, in order to the building of <hi>Zion,</hi> and the lifting up the Lord Jesus unto that Throne of Dignity and Power over all the Earth as he is annointed unto, by the overturning and dissolution of the present state of all Nations and Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in their want of spiritual savor and relish unto a fuller Reformation of things, and unto them that seek and expect such things.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in that they had sometimes escaped the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Anti-christian Ministry, Lordly prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, rigid imposing principles, plurality of places, greediness of Lucre, Men-pleasing, Time-serving practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, living in pleasures, sitting, lying down, loving to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45673:19"/> slumber; but they are now again entangled therein, and seem to be so well pleased in the present polluted state of things, as that they are become dead to those desires and workings of heart after those better promises of good things to come on earth, that they sometimes pressed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: thus are many of our Stars fallen from heaven, as a fig-tree casteth her untimely fruit; whereby we may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern some signs of the times that are upon us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sin of the Churches.</head>
               <p>VVHosoever shall cast an observing eye upon the Churches, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e purest Churches, may find in them also the folly and desertion that at this day is come upon us; let not his words be an offence, who d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es and has born a dear affection towards them from thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>west state; concerning them I have this to say in their praise, that their beginning was small and contemned of men, but owned of God; some clearer beam of Gospel-truth it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that at first led them forth to seek a more perfumed bed of love for the Lord, a more undefiled way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and fellowship than the loose and National way was, wherein the Prophetical and Kingly Offices of Christ might be more owned and exercised in setting him up as sole Law-giver in all his Churches, and in giving liberty to his Spirit to speak by whom it listed; then was there a lively presence of the Lord among them, giving them light and favours unity among themselves, and harmony of spirit with the Administrations of Providence; and many other Ornaments of beauty and comliness he put upon them, making them who at first were as a little branch, to encrease and spread until they had covered the face of the Nation.</p>
               <p>But whereas these Gifts were given of God, as first-fruits and beginnings of a more excellent state, and as the Manna to those in the Wilderness, as comforts and helps for edifying of the Body, and for the following of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45673:19"/> Lord in those further works he had to do; instead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this good use of them, they sate down in these Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness privileges, and became rich and full therein, and bestowed them upon their lusts; some decking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with them to seek honor; others using them for strife and debate, to make a rent in the Body; some ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Merchandize of them; and others abusing them to wantonness and liberty in the flesh; all placing their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and rest in these things, few seeking that true rest which is in Christ himself.</p>
               <p>Whil'st they were little, and in a low condition, then the Lord was pretious, his Laws, Government, and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est were preferred above all: then they saw the frame of things that then was, to be a corrupted thing, and that a separation from it, and the seeking after a more Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical state of things, was that which the Lord called for at their hands: but now that they are grown to be eminent and considerable in the World, their Members become Lords and Rulers, Masters, Tryers, Jaylors, Officers and Exactors every where, these new promotions, such as they are, have so far blinded their eyes, that they have lost that light and sight they sometimes had of better things, new Church, new Government, new King, and a renewed state of all things: security in their gifts and privileges, and glory with men, having so filled and stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their hearts, that they are become dead unto those fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and higher hopes they had before.</p>
               <p>When their elder sister the Presbytery, which run well in the beginning, began to stint light, and Reformation unto their way alone, and did engage the Worldly Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers to their Protection herein, this was looked upon by Churches and Christians of further light as a very offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive thing: but now the Churches by stinting Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto their own present state and measure, and stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a corrupt and worldly Government for their defence herein, have not only justified <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir elder Sister in all that she has done, but have done far worse, by how much their light and experiences, and Gods appearances
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45673:20"/> with them in order to a better way, have been more than the other had: Where is that first indignation against worldly Court, Church, and Clergy, the Nurseries of darkness and slavery, with all their branches? Where is their Zeal for a Restorement of Spirit to themselves, of Mercy and Justice to all men, and of Liberty to the whole Creation? Where is their first Faith, living upon God, leaning upon Christ, looking for Him, and seeking the Law at his lips? Where is their Mercy and Love towards weak Brethren, the lame, the sick, and tempted ones? What is become of this Spirit? Is not that Old principle, that dark, defiled, and earthly Spirit which was some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cast out, returned again into the house new swept and garnished, and with him seven Spirits worse than the first? Thus the Churches must bear their part in that blame and shame that is done among us, and do partake in that desertion that is upon us, which may be seen herein.</p>
               <p>In the darkness upon their Watchmen that they have no vision; themselves asleep in security and ease, while they are torn by division, and many of their children scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and carried away after worldy lust, or spirits of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusion: I speak not against Church order, nor all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; there are some names at this day who have not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled their garments, who believe and cry and look for the redemption of Israel, whose light, and faith, and zeal shall encrease till it set on fire the new-repaired walls of old Babel that are yet standing among us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The sin of those Christians who are not in Churches.</head>
               <p>AS the sin and defection of this day has entered into the purest Churches, so it is to be found amongst men of clearest Light, and highest pretences: there are not few in this Nation who have not joyned themselves unto any visible Church, although many of them are to be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45673:20"/> esteemed not the least nor meanest Members in the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, of which their single and unassociated condition this accompt may be given; many of these having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a clearer light in the Mysterie of the Gospel than the generality of others had, and a sight of a more spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual life and communion with God, and of more unity, largness, and love to all Saints, than most (I say not all) in the Churches were grown up unto, upon this ground they reserved themselves free from Church-relation unto those further Truths, Enjoyments, and Wayes they had already a taste of, and were in hope with all Saints to comprehend and attain unto; in this state while they lived and leaned upon God alone, and kept themselves as chast virgins for Christ, not taking to themselves any covering of flesh, self-glorying, self-righteousness, parts, gifts, or worldly Interests, but the Lord only for their righteousness, and salvation, then had they spiritual eye-sight to discern the darkness and corruption that was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all things, and so look for that better and perfecter state of things promised, that the Lord would come as consuming fire against <hi>Babylon,</hi> as a Finer among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves and the Churches, dissolving these old heavens and earth, and setting up new heavens and new earths, a new Church and new government, wherein dwelleth righteousness, and then they were afraid of sitting down, or setling in any thing before the Lord and his righteousness.</p>
               <p>But Satan, that can transform himself as an Angel of Light, has mingled their Wine with Water, their Spirits and spiritual Principles with his refined witchcrafts, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophical Notions, wandering speculations of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head out of Christ crucified, loosing the simplicity of the Gospel in Allegories; by which means too many are puft up with their knowledge as excelling others, and their hearts stoln away from the Lord, and their minds from the Faith to the idols of the brain; and have so far lost that humble, lively, active Spirit, that Faith and savour in a crucified Christ they sometimes had; that they are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45673:21"/> scattered and fallen back, some into Mystical legality, some into the world, and others into a flatness and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of heart as to any further work for Christ, whilst a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother people among us reckoned by these in a far lower form in the School of Christ have a Spirit upon them to cry unto the Lord for the perfecting of that work he has so gloriously begun amongst us: So that we may say, How are our beautiful things become a wilderness? How are our Goodly stones, Army, Rulers, Teachers, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and orhers that seemed by the Spirit of Grace, by afflictions, and by signal Providences to be prepared for the building, how are they now covered in the rubbish, and the lines of Confusion and Stones of Emptiness stretched over them.</p>
               <p>And thus he that in the first and purest Gospel-ages placed his abomination to stand where it ought not, in Churches, Ordinances, Spiritual Gifts, and Souls of men, has done the like in these dayes, having corrupted our graces and mercies, the most Reformed parties and things among us; and having perverted things that were given for good to be to our hurt; so that instead of improving our good Beginnings unto a further growth and maturity, our light and deliverances unto further light and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, we are set down at ease therein, pleasing our selves in present things; those better things reserved as yet with Christ in God to be brought forth in their sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for them that wait and believe, and those works that are to be done in order to the making way thereto being forgotten and no more pressed after: And so (I wish I could not say it) we are degenerated into that old, dark, and Egyptian Spirit that we seemed to have escaped, wh ch consisted herein; — in the putting a stint and stop unto any further light and further Reformation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove what their carnal Principles and Interests would bear; —and in a compliance with, and clasping about the Powers of the World for their defence therein, and for the pting a check upon all further Truth and Reformation, enwh at consisted with the safety of their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45673:21"/> place, order, and nation, and such-like worldly Interests; which course as it was the ruine of them that are already fallen, so it will prove to this generation if they repent not, and do their first works.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What Dispensation that is, that can bring Healing to us.</head>
               <p>HAving hitherto made some search of what nature is that wound we have received from the Lord, and what are the evils which have procured it, it will much concern us to enquire where Healing may be had for us, or what foundation may be laid which may set us in such a condition of righteousness, peace, and settlement, as shall not be subject to be corrupted, or shaken any more. There is a Principle, which as it has been of blessed use to us in the late works of Providence among us, so it may give good Light to us in this Enquiry, which is this; — That the appearance of Jesus Christ in his Grace and Glory, and the advancement of him as King over all the earth, that is, so as that all foundations raised for the Interest either of worldly Tyranny, or Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Worship be thrown down; and that all things both in Church and Government, do submit themselves to be ordered by the Presence and Word of the Lord among his people; that this is the great Result intended by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in those over-turnings which have been, and may yet come to pass among us. — Their eyes are grown dim, who of late begin to say, That there was no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end in the late Turns of Providence among us, than the preservation of Gods People in a worldly freedom and peace, that they be not destroyed either by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy, or by divisions among themselves: As Light and Reformation has come forth at sundry seasons, and in divers measures; so in any Nation where God had any work of this kind to bring forth, he gave no quiet unto that Church or Government that was therein, untill they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45673:22"/> submitted themselves unto that measure of Light and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation intended for that Age, and People.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This Principle being laid for a Foundation, these Conclusions do with clearness follow:</head>
               <p>FIrst, That no kind nor sort of Government whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, though acting upon the most just and righteous Principles, can administer healing or lasting peace unto us, whil'st it yields not it self in subjection unto the great determinations and works of Providence among us, in a subservient co-working with the Lord in the plucking up the remaining Walls of great <hi>Babel</hi> yet standing, and in making way for those better things which Prophesies of old, Providences of late, and the present Expectation of a waiting People are in travel with: if it may be admitted, that God has a great work to do among us (as who will not blush to deny) and that all civil Administrations are like to stand or fall, according as they shall be found sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thereunto or otherwayes; then no form or way of Government whatsoever can bring peace to it self or the people, whilst the present works of God are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Neither a way of Government reduced as exactly as may be unto the judicial Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> nor any form of Worship, how spiritual soever, considered bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in themselves, can bring healing to us; that form of Government delivered by <hi>Moses,</hi> and that of Worship by the Apostles were in themselves good and excellent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other; but when corruption entered in, and the Lord departed, both the Administrations themselves, and the People under them were scattered, the one into the Literal, the other into the Mystical <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, that the nearer approaching and fuller Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion of Jesus Christ, in the pouring out his Spirit upon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45673:22"/> us, and the taking to himself his great power to raign over us, in the more visible exercise of all his Offices, as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, Law-giver, King and Judge, and a heart waiting for him, and willing to submit all things among us both in Church and State, in an humble and gracious subordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereunto, is that healing Expedient only that can bring redress and cure to all the wounds and breaches whether civil or spiritual that are upon us: I remember what <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sea</hi> saies, <hi>chap.</hi> 10.3. <hi>For now they shall say, we have no King, because we feared not the Lord, what then should a King do to us?</hi> And <hi>chap.</hi> 13.10. <hi>I will be thy King, where is any other that may save thee in all thy Cities, and thy Judges, of whom thou saidst, give me a King and Princes?</hi> If any that are set down at ease in the present privileges God has bestowed upon us, shall promise themselves peace therein; or if any others that are sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible the present state of things to be a bed too short to rest in, shall hope to find peace for the people by some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way or form of worldly Administration; let all such know, it is not in parties or privileges to have or give peace, whil'st the Lord is not admitted as King and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our among us, whose rising only is that which shall bring healing to the Nations.</p>
               <p>That such a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>spensation as this shall be, and that more universal and glorious than any before it has been; since the sayings of the Prophets and Apostles, are by many not so understood and believed; let an observation obvious and plain to all men be our Argument herein, which is this: That the three hundred years last past, have been a season wherein Light and Truth have visited this Western World in a succession of Administrations, the latter still exceeding the former; in all which, the Lord Jesus has been gradually brought to light, and by which he has still gained ground upon that Anti-christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an state, that hath a long time ruled the world: the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himself to light, and the stretching forth of the line of his dominion over all parties and interests whatsoever, in order to the regaining the utmost ends of the Earth to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45673:23"/> himself, having been his design in all his spiritual and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential Administrations, at divers seasons and in seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral degrees that have been upon us: wherefore we may conclude, the Lord will not cease prosecuting his former method, to shake and distress all Nations, Governments, Parties and Interests, that hold their Authority, Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance, or Place in a dependance upon, and for a sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port unto that Mother of Whoredomes, the Anti-christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an State; until the Kingdoms of this World become the Kingdoms of our Lord and his Christ.</p>
               <p>That such a Dispensation as this, is that only that can heal us, and the Nations: our present Experience may be instead of all other Arguments to bring us under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction: if any inferiour privileges or blessings could save us, below the Lords shining, saving and raigning Presence among us, the People of God in this Nation have had a larger measure of Privileges than many Ages before, than all the Nations of the World besides have at this day: Yet how dead and carnal? How far from a tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spiritual, reformed, and raigning State we are at this day, in the midst of all the Victories, Salvations and other favors we are set down in? Let the surfeiting in pompe and pleasure, and the cares of this life, and smiting our fellow servants, the new Confedracies with the old, rotten Interests, visible upon many among all sorts, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disposition that is almost upon us all unto a more tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough redress and Reformation be a witness against us: wherefore though many Eenemies are fallen, yet we are not saved, because the Lord is not King among us, we will not have him to raign over us.</p>
               <p>Now by what means the Lord Jesus arising as the Sun of Righteousness will work healing for the Nations, the great effects that shall go before and attend his Coming do shew, which are these two; <hi>the making all old things to pass away, and the making all things new:</hi> As all the several dispensations of Light and Truth, have in their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral seasons, brought an Earthquake upon that part of the World where they were brought forth: so that fuller
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45673:23"/> and more glorious Revelation of the Lord Jesus in his healing Grace and raigning glory reserved for these last times, inasmuch as it shall spread it self far and wide o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the Earth, shall shake and take down the whole frame of things as now in Church and Government, all States and Interests every where: and as a worthy man sometimes banished for the Testimony of Christ, writes; <hi>The Change in the Heavens and Earth, is meant a change in the qualities, and face, and fashion of all things, in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Common weales, Kingdoms and Nations; the old rotten frame of all things in Religions and Governments shall be broken down in Earthquakes, turning all the World up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side down, so as it must be all made new again; the old fashion of Church and World being waxen old; as a Moth-eaten ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment, having so many Mothes fretting in it, as not a sound part left in it, good for any thing, cannot abide a ffake or pull, but falls in pieces. Therefore it must be laid by as men do old cloathes, quite worn in pieces; and then he that laid the first foundations of the World, will make all new a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain:</hi> Which is the second Effest of his Coming, a new state of things, the street whereof of Gold, and her gates of Pearle, and no Temple was seen therein, for the Lord God Almighty, and the Lamb are the Temple of it; and there is no need neither of the Sun, nor of the Moon to shine in it, for the glory of God shall lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof: happy are they who know how to use the present state of things so, as that they be not hindered thereby (as many at this day are) from pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing on towards those better things, and that Grace that is to be brought forth at the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ, which in his times he shall shew who is the blessed and onely Potentate, King of Kings and Lord of Lords: to whom be Dominion, Honor, and Glory for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>